Guide to the Edward A. Tiryakian Papers, 1963-2008
Duke University. University Archives
Edward A. Tiryakian papers 1963-2008
Duke University. University Archives
Tiryakian, Edward A.
2.75 linear feet Extent: approx. 1,750 Items
Dr. Edward Tiryakian taught in the Department of Sociology from 1965 until his retirement in 2004. He served as Chair of the Department in addition to positions as Visiting Professor abroad. He was appointed Director for the Center of International Studies in 1988 and served until 1991. The collection contains correspondence and materials related to the Dept. of Sociology, and the Center for International Studies as well as memoranda, clippings and correspondence regarding general University business but also the Nixon Presidential Library controversy and the Allen Building Takeover. The collection ranges in date from 1963-2008.
uatirya
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Collection is housed in off-site storage; 48 hours advanced notice is required for retrieval.
Provenance
The Edward A. Tiryakian Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1998 and 2008.
Biographical Note
Edward A. Tiryakian was born August 6, 1929 in Bronxville, NY to Armenian-born parents. Educated in the United States and in France, he received his B. A. in sociology from Princeton University where he was awarded a Phi Beta Kappa key. He earned both his M. A. and his Ph.D. at Harvard University, in 1954 and 1956 respectively. He also held a Fulbright grant at the University of the Philippines during 1954-1955.
In 1965, Dr. Tiryakian came to Duke University as an Associate Professor and was made a full Professor in 1967. From 1969-1971, he served as Chair of Duke's Department of Sociology and Anthropology. He also served as associate director of Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, 6e Section at the University of Paris from 1971-1972. Additionally, he served as visiting professor at U.E.R. de Sciences Sociales at the Universite Rene Descartes in Paris in 1985 and visiting professor at Laval University in Quebec and adjunct professor at Concordia University in Quebec in 1978.
In 1988, Dr. Tiryakian was appointed Director of International Studies and served in this post until 1991. He continued to research and teach until his retirement as Professor Emeritus in 2004. His publications include the books The Global Crisis: Sociological Analyses and Responses and New Nationalism of the Developed West.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence and materials related to the Dept. of Sociology and the Center for International Studies as well as memoranda, clippings and correspondence regarding general University business and committees but also the Nixon Presidential Library controversy and the Allen Building Takeover. Some of the files are restricted. The collection ranges in date from 1963-2008.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Center for International Studies; Duke University. Dept. of Sociology -- Faculty; Duke University -- Committees; Duke University. Nixon Library Controversy; Duke University. Allen Building Takeover; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.).
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection4
Duke University Archives
Center for International Studies Records
Duke University Archives
Dept. of Sociology Records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1968-1992 (Box 1)
  - Dept. of Sociology - Curricula, Syllabi, Exams, late 1970s-early 1980s, 2000
  - Dept. of Sociology - Memoranda and Reports, 1966-2001 (Restricted)
  - Dept. of Sociology - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1966, 1968, 1969, 1974, 1975, 1998 and Chair's Report, 1998 (Restricted)
  - Center for International Studies - Correspondence, 1984-1991, 1996
  - Center for International Studies - Reports, Newsletters, Miscellany, 1977-1991
  - Program in Quebec Studies at Duke, 1979-1986, 1995
  - Canadian Studies, 1980, 1986-1987
  - Duke-McGill Conference, 1983 May
  - Duke - Socio-Political events, including Nixon Presidential Library controversy and Allen Building takeover, 1968-1971, 1981
  - "Sociology at Duke University," Edgar T. Thompson
  - Wallace Fowlie, 1987, 1998
  - Academic Council - Committee to Review Appointment, Promotion and Tenure, 1980-1985 (Restricted)
  - Academic Council/Univeristy Faculty, 1972, 1978, 1984 (Restricted)
  - Committee on African Studies - Minutes, 1967 Jan. 12
  - Residential Life, 1967-1968
  - Academic Priorities Committee, 1985-1986
  - Faculty Newsletter, 1984 Sept., 1985 Sept.
  - Duke - General
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1993-1996, 2001
  - Committee on National Identity, Nationalism and Ethnicity - Correspondence, 1996-1997
  - Committee on National Identity, Nationalism and Ethnicity - General, 1996-1997
  - NEH Summer Seminar for College Teachers (Duke University), 1996
  - Berlin [visiting professorship at Free Univ. of Berlin], 1996
  - Beta Chapter, Phi Beta Kappa, 1977-1980, 1985, 1988, 1996-1997
  - Clippings, 1963-1981
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2008
  - Travel to Africa, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Program in Quebec Studies, 1979-1983 (3 folders)
  - Quebec Studies at Duke, 1978-1982 (2 folders)
  - Africana, 1964, 1969
  - "Good Surprises" Conference, 1995 Nov.
  - Social Context of Conservative Thought, 1969
  - Edgar Thompson, circa 1973-1989
  - Departmental File: Material Collected as Chair, 1969-1971
  - Harold Parker, circa 1982-1989, 1991, 1995 (Box 3)
  - S.N. Eisenstadt, 1999-2003
  - International Studies, 1970s-1990s (2 folders)
  - Correspondence with the Allen Building, 1970s-1980s
  - American Society for the Study of Religion, 1982-1985
  - Clippings (5 folders) (Box 4)